A phone cannot achieve all of the following at the same time:
一个手机它是没有办法同时做到
Exceptional performance,
性能非常非常好
and outstanding battery life.
续航又非常好
It's also very portable
同时便携也很好的
How to put it
怎么说呢
When a phone's performance is pushed to the max
就是当一个手机的性能拉到最满
while still maintaining great battery life
同时续航也很好
it means you can use it for a lot
也就是能玩
like playing games for 20 hours straight
比如说连续玩20个小时
it's inevitable that the phone won't be compact
那么必然它这个手机就不可能很小巧
because the battery takes up a lot of space
因为它的电池会占很大的面积
if a phone has excellent performance
那么如果一个手机它的性能很好
It's also very portable
便携也很好
The phone is quite compact
手机很小巧
Then its battery life would inevitably be a bit of an issue
那么它的续航必然就会有些问题
Because it just can't last for a long time
因为它就没有办法撑很长的时间
Now, if a phone has great battery life
那么假设一个手机它的续航也很好
It's also very portable
便携性也很好
It would have to sacrifice some performance
它就势必要牺牲一部分的性能
For instance, even if its SOC doesn't have a significant impact
比如说哪怕它的SOC没有太大的影响
But its camera module couldn't be that large
但是它的相机模组就不可能那么大
This is the impossible triangle on a smartphone
这个是手机上面的不可能三角
In fact, there are many other impossible triangles
实际上还有很多其他的不可能三角
For instance, in the municipal transportation sector
比如说在市政交通领域
In a transportation system
一个交通系统中
It's impossible to have a very high average speed for vehicles while also having a high road utilization rate with a lot of cars packed into the same lanes extremely congested and with a low accident rate
你是没有办法让车辆的平均速度非常高 同时呢道路的利用率又很大 就是同样的车道内挤了非常多的车啊 非常拥挤以及事故率很低的
You can't achieve that
你是做不到的
When everyone drives fast in a city's traffic system,
当一个城市的交通系统大家开的都很快
and the roads are also very congested,
同时道路又有又很拥挤的时候
the accident rate can't possibly be low.
事故率必然不可能很低
Let me give another example.
那再举个例
Take our profession, for instance,
比如说呃我们这个职业啊
UPloaders or video bloggers,
up主或者说视频博主
it's impossible to simultaneously maintain a very high update frequency,
视频博主是没有办法同时满足更新频率非常快
very high content quality,
内容质量非常高
and a very strong originality.
同时原创性非常强的
Assuming you can update daily
假设你能做到日更
and your content quality is exceptionally high
你的内容质量又非常好
then it's highly likely
那么极有可能啊
that your content heavily draws from many peers
你的内容实际上是借鉴了大量的同行
and is compiled and summarized
然后整理归纳得来的
or when your update frequency
那或者当你的这个更新频率
can quickly reach a daily update
很快能能够达到日更
with strong originality
原创性也很强
all written by yourself
都是自己写的时候
Then the quality of your content won't be as good as it could be
那么你的内容质量就不可能非常非常好
For instance, you apply the same methodology to different trending topics
比如说你就是拿同一套方法论套进不同的热点
Just repeating the same old clichés
车轱辘话来回说说片汤话啊
This is a very common and normal phenomenon
这个是常见的非常正常的一种现象
So this video starts with the concept of the impossible triangle
那么这期视频呢就从不可能三角开始
We'll delve deeper layer by layer
我们层层的递进
Let's play a thought experiment or a mind game And keep pushing to uncover the essence To see what it really is What kind of insights can it bring us? This is likely the most in-depth one you can find online.
我们玩一个思维推演或者思维游戏 然后不停的把把本质往下推 看看它到底是什么 能给我们带来什么样的启示 那这很有可能是你全网能够找到的最深的
Some breakdowns of the impossible triangle.
关于不可能三角的一些拆解
And reflections.
还有思考
First, let's look at the essence of the impossible triangle.
首先看不可能三角的本质到底是什么
The first level.
第一层
At the first level, we can see a multitude of impossibilities.
第一层呢是我们可以看到非常多的不可能
The triangle can be abstracted into three elements.
三角可以抽象成三个要素
The first element is efficiency.
第一个要素是效能
The second factor is Space
第二个要素是啊空间
The third factor is Time
第三个要素是时间
These three factors often conflict with each other
那么这三个要素之间是存在矛盾的
The first efficiency
那么第一个效能呢
can often be represented as performance or benefit
在很多时候也可以呈现为啊性能或者收益
or efficiency or score
或者效率或者得分
Space can also be abstracted as scale
空间呢很多时候也能抽象成规模
including the scope of application of something
包括一个事情的适用范围
or the coverage of a feature
包括一种功能的覆盖度
The target audience
覆盖人群
Or we can flip it around
或者我们把它反过来
It can also be abstracted as the necessary expenditure
也可以抽象成所所必须花的成本啊
Because cost and scale are actually interrelated factors
因为成本和规模实际上也是一个相关的要素
Time, for instance, can be the physical duration
那么时间呢它既可以是物理的持续时间
Or it can be the risk involved Or the success rate Because as the risk increases The duration inevitably cannot be very long So, after abstracting from numerous impossible triangles, it comes down to efficiency, the contradiction between Space, and time.
也可以是一件事的风险 或者说成功率 因为风险大了以后 持续时间就必然没有办法很长嘛 那么非常多的不可能三角最后抽象完了 就是效能 空间和时间三者之间的一个矛盾
Let's move on to the next level.
好我们再往下推一层
The second level.
第二层
The second level is about the impossibility,
第二层呢是不可能
the essence of the triangle.
三角的本质
We can view it as,
我们可以看作是
when a system has three elements that are pairwise negatively correlated.
当系统中有有三个两两负相关的要素的时候
These elements will compete for weight with each other
这些要素之间会互相争抢权重啊
As a result, they can't all be maximized at the same time
于是他们没有办法同时拉到最满
Or let me put it another way
或者呢我换一个视角
When there are three elements in the system that are pairwise negatively correlated
也是当系统中有三个两两负相关要素的时候
Each element can essentially
实际上每一个要素都可以
Be transformed through the other two
通过另外两个要素转化得来
One always has to consider
他总是要想
What sacrifices I need to make to boost one or two metrics
我为了拉升某一个到两个指标
What cost I need to pay
我需要支付什么样的代价
I hope to enhance a particular benefit at the cost of one or two factors.
我希望以一个或者两个要素的代价
This is essentially the kind of decision-making process people engage in.
去提升某一项收益
Let's delve a bit deeper.
实际上大家做的是这样的一种决策
Let's go even further down.
我们再往下推一层啊
Why is the impossible triangle so frustrating?
再往下推一层
Why can't we have everything we want? Because the physical world is subject to increasing entropy. Because the second law of thermodynamics governs this world. Because the second law of thermodynamics exists in this world. So what does the Second Law of Thermodynamics tell us?
这个世界为什么有不可能三角为什么这么讨厌 为什么我们没有办法既要又要还要 因为物理世界是熵增的 因为这个世界上是有热力学第二定律的 那么热力学第二定律告诉我们什么
It tells us that over time,
就是随时间的推移
a closed or isolated system will inevitably experience an increase in entropy.
一个封闭或者孤立的系统一定会熵增
This increase in entropy has two manifestations.
熵增有两个表现形式
The first manifestation is that
第一个表现形式是
the disorder within the system will continually rise.
这个系统中的无序度会不断的上升
The accumulated risks will continue to expand.
积累的风险会不断的扩大
Eventually, the system will collapse.
那么最终系统会崩溃
It cannot sustain itself indefinitely.
它没有办法持续下去
The second manifestation is the different elements within this system
那么第二个表现形式是这个系统中不同的要素
They rapidly transform and flow between each other
它们之间会快速的转化和流动
Ultimately leading to a decrease in free energy
最终导致自由能下降
Which means the system's vitality diminishes
也就是系统的活力下降
And it becomes a state of lifelessness
然后变成一种死寂的状态
A state of rigidity
变成一种僵化的状态
This also means the system cannot be sustained
也导致了这个系统是无法持续的
This might sound a bit too abstract
好这么说可能有点太抽象
Let me give you some examples
我举一些例子
What is the increase in disorder leading to entropy?
什么是无序度上升导致熵增
Then what about the situation where the system can no longer continue?
然后系统无法继续的情况呢
For example, let's look at NBA players.
比如说啊我们看NBA的球员
Their playing time, their contribution on the court, and their health cannot be guaranteed simultaneously. You can't ensure all of these aspects at the same time. It means you can't play over 40 minutes every game. You can't push your body to the limit without regard for the consequences. That means making contributions on both offense and defense.
他的上场时间和他的场上贡献度和它的健康度 是没有办法同时保证 也就是你没有办法每场上40多分钟 然后呢你不计代价的去使用你自己的身体 也就是攻防两端都有贡献
Being fully committed
非常的投入
No slacking off
毫不摸鱼
and on the court
然后在场上呃
blocking, rebounding, and scoring with all my might
这个盖帽篮板得分都全力以赴
the intensity on the court is maxed out
在场上对抗拉满啊
speed is also at its peak
速度也拉满
this way, your injuries will inevitably accumulate
这样的话你的伤病势必就会积累
the accumulation of injuries is essentially the buildup of disorder
伤病积累实际上就是无序度积累
eventually leading to system failure
最终导致系统崩溃
what kind of system failure?
什么系统崩溃呢
It's your body system that's breaking down
是你的身体系统崩溃
Now, in the municipal traffic system we mentioned earlier
另外呢刚才所说的市政交通这个系统里面
When everyone is driving very fast on the roads
当道路上面大家车开得都很快的时候
And the roads are extremely congested
同时道路非常拥挤的时候
Given that the world is subject to increasing entropy
那么因为这个世界是熵增的
Drivers are bound to make mistakes
那么必然司机会有不小心的情况
The system is bound to experience disturbances
必然系统会有扰动
Which in turn increases the risk
然后导致风险增大
Thus, accidents will occur on the roads
于是这个道路中就会出现事故
After accidents pile up
出现事故多了以后
it simply can't function properly anymore
实际上他就没有办法运转了
In the case of municipal traffic
那么在市政交通的这个例子里面
if everyone is moving at high speeds
如果大家的通行速度都非常快
and the roads are congested
然后呢道路又很拥挤
the margin for error is very low
容错率就会很低
and people can't afford to make mistakes but no matter how careful you are mistakes will inevitably happen Whether it's due to mechanical failure or due to the driver's carelessness the accident rate is bound to rise This is due to the risk accumulated within the system
大家又不能犯错 但是人不管你多么的小心 一定是会犯错的 那么不管是由于机械故障 还是由于驾驶员的不小心 它事故率一定会往上走 这个是系统内积累的风险导致的好
The second form of entropy increase is the decline in free energy, right?
第二种熵增形式是自由能下降对吧
What does that mean?
什么意思呢
In reality, it means within this system
实际上就是这个系统中
through the natural flow between its various components
通过它的各种要素之间的自然流动
more competitors are entering to do the same thing
涌入了更多的竞争者来跟你做同样的事情
This leads to a continuous reduction in the space where you can act.
导致你能够做事情的空间不断的下降
Eventually, you won't be able to get things done.
最后呢你就干不了事了
For example, let's take a smartphone.
比如说我们还拿手机来说
A smartphone can't do this.
手机这个不可能
The triangle is actually a classic example of a decrease in free energy.
三角实际上就是自由能下降的一个典范
That is, when performance is pushed to an extreme level.
也就是当你的性能拉到非常大的时候
At the same time, the battery is very small.
同时电池又很小
So as you use it, the chemical energy gets depleted.
那么你用着用着化学能耗尽了
Then the potential difference inside is leveled out.
然后其中的电位差抹平了
Then the phone can't discharge anymore
那么手机就没有办法放电了
As a result, the system collapses
于是这个系统就瘫痪了
For example, in the business world
还有呢比如说呃在商业领域啊
When we start a business
我们做一个生意
You'll find it hard to find one
你会发现你很难找到
With a high profit margin
利润率又很高
And the business has a large scale
然后呢这个生意的规模很大
For instance, it's not just a daily income of 1,000
比如说不是每天只能有1000收入
Its maximum annual revenue
它一年它的营收最多
If done well, it can reach hundreds of millions. The market size is substantial. Moreover, its certainty is also high. You won't find such an opportunity elsewhere. Why is there such an impossible triangle? Because you're not the only one doing business in this market.
做得好的话可以上亿 市场规模很大 同时呢它的确定性还很高 你是找不到这样的机会的 为什么会有的这样的不可能三角呢 是因为这个市场上不是只有你一个人在做生意
The market factors are constantly in flux.
这个市场上要素是在不断流动的
Information is continuously flowing.
信息是在不断不断流动的
Assuming a business has a great scale
假设一个生意它的规模很好
The wealthy and the smart
富人还有聪明人
as well as those who are very capable
还有很厉害的人
all see the potential
都看得惯
and recognize the high market certainty
看得上这块市场确定性也很高
everyone knows that this field can make money
大家都知道这个领域能发财啊
like the current AI sector
像比如说现在的AI领域
which means the competition will be intense
那么势必它的竞争就会很大
with fierce competition
竞争很大
profit margins will be squeezed
利润率就会被压下来
So, there actually exists a window of opportunity within this.
所以呢这其中其实际上存在一个窗口期
This is a period when the market can simultaneously achieve very high profit margins,
也就是在这个市场上能够同时达到利润率很高
a large scale,
规模很大
and a high level of certainty, but such a window is fleeting.
确定性又很高的窗口期是转瞬即逝的
Why?
为什么
Because the information gap is quickly closed through the flow of resources.
因为很快通过要素的流动信息差就抹平了
As a result, the potential for profit diminishes,
于是自由能下降
and you won’t find such opportunities anymore.
你就找不到这样的机会了
What I’ve described is
上面所说的是
Why the impossible triangle can't exist in large numbers
为什么不可能三角大量存在
is because the world is in a state of increasing entropy
就是因为这个世界是熵增的好
Let's delve a bit deeper
我们再往下推一层啊
The fourth layer is the impossibility
第四层是不可能
Is the impossible triangle truly impossible?
三角真的是完全不可能吗
Many people might not fully grasp this And thus have this impression Since it's called the impossible triangle It implies that We can never pursue these three elements simultaneously. But observing real life reveals that.
很多人可能理解不深的话 会有这样的印象 就是你都叫不可能三角了 那么也就是意味着 我们我们永远不可能同时追求这三个要素 但不是你看现实生活就能发现
For example, the UPloader I mentioned earlier.
比如说啊刚才说的up主
This impossible triangle, right?
这个不可能三角对吧
Update frequency,
更新频率
Originality,
原创性
and content quality.
包括内容质量
Compared to me, Luo Xiang
那罗翔和我相比
has a faster update frequency.
他的更新频率既比我快
The content quality is also higher than mine
同时呢内容质量也比我高
In terms of originality
原创性啊
His originality is on par with mine
跟原创性跟我一样啊
It’s all in his own words
都是他自己的话
He’s got a bigger edge in all three aspects
他三个角都比我大
We talked about the player's playing time
刚才说到了这个球员上场时间啊
Contribution and injuries
贡献度还有伤病
Compared to me, Jordan
那乔丹相比于我
If we were to play in the same game
我们如果他打同一场比赛的话
He has more playing time than me
他既比我上场时间多
and he also contributes more
同时呢他也比我贡献度大
and he is healthier
同时他还比我更健康
with a lower risk of injury
伤病的概率更小
he excels in all three aspects compared to me
它也是三个角同时强于我
or let's take a look at smartphones
或者呢我们来看手机
today's phones compared to those from two years ago
现在的手机和两年前的手机相比
could very well have better performance
它完全有可能性能也更好
and better battery life
续航也更好
And it's also lighter and thinner.
同时它也更轻薄
This is entirely possible.
这是完全有可能的
So why is this the case?
所以为什么会这样呢
Or perhaps we should approach it from a different angle and think in reverse. We often find that many capabilities fall short. Or in systems with limited resources. You might find yourself in an impossible dilemma. Or we could call it a false dichotomy.
啊或者呢我们换一个思路再去逆向思考 我们会发现在很多能力不行 或者资源有限的系统中 你是会陷入不可能二角的 或者说我们可以把它叫做虚假两难两难
When a phone company is relatively inexperienced.
当一个手机公司比较菜的时候
Just addressing the conflict between performance and battery life
它光是解决性能和续航之间的矛盾
is already a tough challenge
它就已经没法办了
meaning if the performance is good
也就是性能好
the battery life will inevitably be poor
续航一定差
and if you want to improve battery life
续航想要拉高
you have to compromise on performance
性能一定得降低
like when a player isn't very skilled
包括当一个球员很菜的时候
for instance, just balancing my playing time and contribution
比如说我光是上场时间和贡献度
I can't have both
我就没有办法两全
Why
为什么
Because my physical condition only allows me to last for a quarter of an hour
因为我的体能只够支撑一刻钟
If I want to have a higher contribution
那我如果想要贡献度高的话
I have to reduce my playing time
那我就必须得压低我的上场时间
This is not a false dichotomy
这个是不可能二缴或者叫虚假两难
So from the examples above
所以呢通过上面的例子
I believe you can see
我相信大家已经看出来了
The impossible triangle is actually a special case of an impossible N-gon
不可能三角其实是不可能N角的一种特殊形态
Impossible triangles do exist in this world
这个世界上存在不可能三角
Impossible triangle
不可能二角
Impossible quadrilateral
不可能四角
There's even an impossible pentagon
甚至有不可能五角
So, to turn an impossible N-sided shape into an impossible N+1-sided shape
那么从不可能N角变成不可能N加一角
What needs to be done?
需要做到什么呢
How can we break the deadlock?
怎么样去破局呢
Actually, there are two approaches
其实有两种思路
One approach is to break the deadlock with force
一种思路是以力破局
That is, when you're out of options within the system You introduce negative energy from outside the system to revitalize it internally. Sometimes, this approach can achieve a triple win. Another strategy is to break the deadlock with ingenuity.
也就是当这个系统内你已经没辙的时候 你从系统外部引入负伤去往里输血 那么有的时候就能够同时做到三个角 那还有一种思路呢是以巧破局
This means you don’t rely on external forces.
也就是你不从系统外部去借力
Instead, you enhance the internal system’s capabilities.
但是呢你提高这个系统内部
By improving the efficiency of converting different elements within the system,
不同要素的转化效率
you can also break the deadlock.
你也能够破局
This might sound too abstract,
这样说的可能太过抽象
so let me give you an example.
我举个例子
Like the UPloader I mentioned just now, right?
比如说我刚才说到的up主对吧
Even UPloaders can't manage to do all of these at the same time.
up主都没有办法同时做到啊
Maintain high content quality,
内容质量又好
update frequently,
更新频率又高
and be highly original.
原创性又高
So, how can we break this deadlock?
那怎么样去破这个局呢
For a thinking system like mine,
对于我这样的一个思维系统来说
I might have reached my limits.
我可能已经做到极限了
But I can build a team.
但是我可以组建团队
Building a team
组建团队
is actually about getting other teammates to contribute to this creation system
实际上是让别的小伙伴给我这个创作系统
for comfort
舒服上
so I can ensure the quality of the content
于是我能在保证内容质量
while maintaining originality
保证原创性的基础上
and then increase my update frequency, right?
然后把我的更新频率提上去对吧
This impossible triangle is thus broken
这个不可能三角就破了
What I mentioned earlier was breaking the deadlock with resources
刚才说的是以利破局
So what does breaking the deadlock with ingenuity mean?
以巧破局是什么呢
I might have learned something new
我有可能去学习了一些东西
I might have explored some new fields
我有可能去学习了一些领域
As a result, my knowledge has grown
于是我的积累提升了
Consequently, my creative methodology has improved Or I might have discovered a fresh perspective This situation could also change For instance, I wouldn't speak in such a boring way I could incorporate some talk show techniques This way, I can ensure my show is highly engaging
于是呢我的创作方法论提升了 或者我找到了新的创作视角 这个局也有可能破 比如说我说话不像现在一样无聊 我引入一些脱口秀的做做法 我既能保证我这个节目非常好看
In a sense, the quality is very high.
某种意义上质量很高
At the same time, I can increase my update frequency.
同时呢我又可以加快我的更新频率
And all of this content is written by me.
然后这些话还都是我自己写的
This is in the context of the UPloader example.
这个是up主这个例子里面
In the context of the smartphone example, then.
那么手机这个例子里面呢
To break the deadlock with force.
以力破局
It might seem rather mindless.
可能他显得非常的无脑
For instance, cloud computing is a way to break the performance deadlock.
比如说啊云计算就是一种与地破局性能
On this point, I introduce an external service provider.
这个点上我引入一个系统外的服务商
I don't rely on the SOC of the phone
我不是靠手机的soc
nor do I depend on its processing units for computation
不是靠它的运算单元去计算
in fact, I rely on the network
那实际上呢我是靠网络
to bring external computing power into the phone for my use
把外部的算力引入到这个手机借为己用
thus, I can break through this impossible triangle
那于是我就可以突破这个不可能三角
I might be able to make the battery very small
我可能电池能做的很小
but its processing speed doesn't decrease
但是它的运算速度并没有降
what other ways can break the deadlock?
还有什么以利破局的方式呢
for example, I can use this room
比如说我把我这个房间
I've transformed this space so it can be used anywhere.
我这个空间改造成在任何地方
You just place your phone on it.
你把手机放上去
It becomes a room where wireless charging is possible.
都可以进行无线充电的一个房间
So, the phone doesn't need to rely on its internal power all the time.
那么这个手机实际上就不用
It doesn't have to use the energy within its system constantly.
每时每刻都用它系统内的能量
The internal energy source won't be the sole provider for its computations.
系统内的能源来满足它的计算了
This way, the impossible triangle issue can be resolved. This is the brute force approach. The clever approach is to leverage advancements in technology. As our manufacturing processes advance I have a new manufacturing process new material technologies or batteries
那么这个问题不可能三角也会解决掉 这是以力破局的思路 以巧破局的思路呢就是当呃科技往前进步 当我们的制造工艺往前进步 我有了新的制造工艺 新的材料技术或者电池
if energy density can take a step up
能量密度能往上攀一个台阶的话
this impossible triangle can also be broken
这个不可能三角也可以打破好
Let me give another example
那再举一个例子
As I mentioned earlier
就是刚才我说了
In an economic system
在一个经济系统中
if you want to start a business
你想要做一个生意
It's hard to find a business with high profit margins,
你是很难找到利润率又高呃
large scale,
规模又大
and high certainty, right?
同时确定性又高的生意的对吧
Is it even possible?
那有没有可能做到呢
It might have been possible during the early stages of Reform and Opening up,
有可能也就是在改革开放的初期
when we could achieve this.
我们就能做到这一点
Why is that?
那为什么
Because in the early stages of Reform and Opening up,
因为改革开放的初期
the market was continuously expanding.
你可以理解成它的盘子是在不断扩大的
In reality, the system has been continuously fueled by substantial investments from wealthy businessmen.
实际上整个系统是有巨额的富商不断的输入的
So back then, opportunities were everywhere.
所以那个时候到处都是机会
It was a time when gold was lying on the ground, waiting to be picked up.
遍地都是黄金
All you needed was to put in a certain amount of effort.
你只要投入一定的努力
And as long as you were smart,
你只要是个聪明人
you could find opportunities where all three elements were present, right?
你就可以找到这三者都存在的机会对吧
That's why so many legendary entrepreneurs emerged during that time.
所以那个时候也涌现了这么多传奇的企业家
They essentially benefited from the era's advantages.
把实际上是吃到了时代红利
The advantages of that era.
这个时代红利
The so-called era dividend is a massive tycoon.
所谓的时代红利就是一个巨大的富商
Now, let's look at this.
那么我们再看
If we enter an era of economic downturn, if we enter a period of economic downturn, we'll find that it's not possible to attract tycoons from outside, and your market keeps shrinking. So, at this point, it's not even the impossible triangle anymore.
如果到了一个经济下行时代啊 我说如果啊如果到了一个经济下行的周期里面 我们会发现外部不但没有办法输入富商 同时你的盘子还在不断的缩小 所以这个时候甚至不是不可能三角了
It degenerates into its most dangerous or narrowest form.
它退化成了一种最危险的或者最狭窄的形式
It's not about preserving any two of them.
也就是不是说你保住其中的两项
It requires sacrificing something else
需要牺牲另外一个代价
rather than keeping one of them
而是你保住其中的一项
you have to sacrifice the other two
就要牺牲另外两项的代价
For instance, when my company faces a tough year
比如说我这个公司在年景不好的时候啊
in a downturn
在下行的周期里面
I might have to make a very tough decision
我可能要面对一个非常难受的决定
If I want to maintain the profit margin
我如果要保利润率的话
I have to downsize my business
我就得缩小我的生意规模
I have to take a risk
我就得去冒险
If I want to ensure certainty,
我如果要去保确定性的话
I might have to sacrifice my profit margin,
我可能就要牺牲我的利润率
including reducing the size of my company,
包括去减小我这个公司的盘子
or narrowing my business scope.
或者减小我的业务范围啊
At this point, it becomes the most unbearable impossible triangle.
这个时候就变成了一个最最不堪的不可能三角
This is about whether there are negative impacts outside the system,
这个就是系统外有没有负伤
including the elements within your system,
包括你这个系统内的要素
and whether the conversion efficiency has improved sufficiently.
转化效率有没有提高好
What was mentioned earlier is the impossible.
那么刚才所说的就是不可能
Two scenarios for a triangular breakthrough
三角突破的两种情况
Let me repeat that
我再重复一遍
The first is to introduce forces from outside the system Resources from outside the system Wealthy individuals from outside the system The second is to enhance the conversion efficiency Between different elements within the system When your battery has a higher energy density You can actually use less space
第一种是引入系统外的力量 系统外的资源 系统外的富商 第二种呢是提高这个系统内不同要素专 之间的转化效率 你电池的能量密度高了 实际上你就能用更小的空间
Then, to meet higher performance requirements
然后呢满足更多的性能
Achieve longer battery life
实现更长的续航
Wouldn't this factor be improved?
这个要素不就提高了吗
Right?
对吧
So, if we delve a bit deeper
那么呃再往下推一层啊
Go a level deeper
再往下推一层
There are two points to note
有两点要注意的啊
The first point is that even if you break the impossible triangle
第一点是就算你突破了不可能三角
This triangle still exists, in fact
其实这个三角依然是存在的
What does that mean?
什么意思呢
Compared to two years ago,
这款手机相比于两年前
it's possible that its performance, battery life, and portability have all improved.
有可能它的性能续航便携都提升了
But for the current moment,
但是对此时此刻
for phone engineers and designers in 2025,
2025年的手机工程师设计师而言
with the existing technology,
以现有的技术
this phone still can't simultaneously maximize performance and battery life,
实际上这款手机依然没有办法同时把性能续航
as well as portability.
还有便携拉到最满
And compared to Jordan and me,
还有乔丹和我相比啊
His playing time and contributions
他的上场时间贡献度
as well as his health, can all be better than mine
以及他的健康程度都可以比我好
but for himself
但是对他自己来说
if he overly focuses on one aspect
如果他要是畸形的拉高某一方面的表现
for instance, if he wants to minimize his injury risk
比如说他想让自己的伤病概率达到最低
and extend his athletic career to the longest possible to ensure an exceptionally long career he wouldn’t be able to play full minutes every game and go all out in every match So the impossible triangle still exists
他把自己的运动年限拉到最长 嗯保证一个超级长的运动生涯 他就没有办法每场打满 并且每场都在玩命 所以不可能三角其实依然是存在的
It's just that the current triangle has surpassed the previous one
只是说现在的三角突破了之前的三角
Its total area has expanded
它的总面积扩大了而已
This rule still holds true
这个规律依然存在
The second point to note is
那么第二点需要注意的是
If your approach to breaking the deadlock
如果你的这个破局方式
Is not about improving the conversion efficiency between different elements
不是提高不同要素之间的转化效率
But rather you choose to break through with force
而是你选择了以力破局
That is, by introducing wealthy merchants from outside the system
也就是引入系统外的富商
So let's try a different word
那么我们换一个词儿
A word that sounds much worse
换一个很难听的词儿
In fact, you're introducing a new cost that can be sacrificed
实际上你是引入了一个可以被牺牲的新的代价
What does a new dimension mean?
一个新的维度什么意思呢
For example, 996
比如说996
How can we understand this?
我们我们可以怎么去理解这件事
We all know that in project management, there's a famous concept
我们都知道在项目管理中有一个著名的不可能
The impossible triangle
三角
It refers to scope
就是范围
Time and cost
时间和成本啊
You can't simultaneously meet the extensive scope of this project
你没有办法同时满足这个项目的覆盖范围很大
And complete it very quickly
然后呢他完成的速度又很快
While keeping the cost low
然后成本又很低
But what does 996 mean
但是996可以什么意思
In reality, you're introducing a new cost
实际上是你是引入了一个新的代价
If the company doesn't care about the health of its employees
就是如果这个公司不在意员工的健康
And isn't concerned about legal risks You're bringing in an external force that can be sacrificed That is, when the employee is healthy Then the impossible triangle of project management is achieved You still give him the same amount of money for a month
也不在意在意法律风险的时候 你引入了一个可以被牺牲的系统外的力量 也就是员工的健康的时候 那么项目管理的不可能三角就完成了 你同样还是给了他一个月这么多的钱
But he can do more work
但是他能干的活更多了
The cost would naturally decrease, right?
成本不就下降了嘛对吧
Or the time for this project would be shortened, wouldn't it?
或者说这个项目的呃时间不就缩短了吗
The scope would be expanded, wouldn't it?
范围不就扩大了吗
Of course, you could say
啊当然你可以说啊
This is not from outside the system
这个不是系统外的
This is within the system.
这是系统内的
But the employee health introduced
但是引入的员工健康
is actually outside the original company's management scope.
其实是不在原来那个公司管理范围内的
And it actually has health insurance and other aspects
而且它实际上是有医保等等各方面
to cover the cost for him.
去为他支付这个代价的
Or to put it more bluntly,
或者我们说的更损一点儿
he fires you at the age of 30,
他在30岁的时候把你开除了
and you end up outside the system, right?
你不就变成系统外的了对吧
The cost of your health won't be covered by the elements within this system.
你的健康的代价不由他这个系统内的要素吃
So he can break through
所以他就可以突破
the impossible triangle, or it's just a joke
不可能三角或者呢呃有一个说着玩的
the impossible triangle isn't very rigorous
不可能三角不是很严谨啊
If you're looking for a job
就是如果你去找一个工作的话
you can't find one that pays well, has little work
你没有办法同时找到钱多事儿少
and is close to home
离家近
right?
对不对
Actually, some people can find such jobs
其实有的人是可以找到的啊
but let's assume it's impossible
但是我们就当做这个不可能
Triangles are generally valid.
三角是大部分时候都都成立的
So how do you break through?
那怎么突破呢
You can go to your dad's company. Your dad runs the company. Then you join your dad's company. What is the cost of this sacrifice? The cost is your dad's interests. Your dad is paying you. In reality, an unqualified employee is being brought in.
你去你爸的公司就可以了 你爸当当公司老板 然后呢你进你爸的公司 牺牲的是什么代价呢 牺牲的是你爸的利益 你爸为了给你发钱 实际上引入了一个不合格的员工
And the risks for his company have increased.
而且他的公司的风险增大
His other employees might become dissatisfied.
他的其他的员工有可能不满
Once you introduce a cost,
你引入了一个代价之后
the unequal triangle is broken.
这个不等的三角就破了
It’s your impossible triangle that’s broken.
破的是你的不可能三角
And what’s sacrificed is the interests of your father and the company.
然后牺牲的是你爸和公司的利益
So, we see the impossible N-sided shape turn into an impossible N+1-sided shape.
所以呢我们看不可能N角到不可能N加一角
To put it bluntly,
用很难听的话来说
it’s when you can introduce a new element.
就是当你能够引入一个新的
The impossible triangle can be broken
不可能三角就可以破
For example, social development
还有比如说社会发展
You might not be able to achieve efficiency, equity, and equality simultaneously
你可能没有办法同时做到效率公平和平等
Social development
社会发展
These three cannot be achieved at the same time
这三者是没有办法同时做到
But if you significantly sacrifice the environment
但是呢如果你大幅的牺牲环境
If you completely disregard environmental protection
你完全不在意环保
In reality, you are borrowing from the natural system
实际上你是在向自然系统
Borrowing from nature
大自然去借富商
So there's a good chance you can do this well
那么这件事你就有可能的完成好
That's my take on the impossible triangle
那么这个就是我对不可能三角的一些理解啊
I wonder if you all got it
不知道你们有没有听懂
I tried to explain it with the lowest possible barrier to understanding
我觉得我已经用尽可能比较低的理解门槛
to get this point across Now that we know what practical implications does this have for us? A few things come to mind First, you now know After understanding the impossible triangle, you will certainly be able to grasp
去把这件事说出来了 那么知道了 这些能够对我们的现实有什么指导意义呢 我想到几条 第一条就是你知道了 不可能三角理解了这件事之后 你就一定能够明白
that we need to respect the objective laws
实际上我们是要尊重客观规律的
we need to respect the second law of thermodynamics,
我们要尊重热力学第二定律
we need to respect the physical laws in this physical world,
我们要尊重这个物理世界中的物理规律
and we also need to respect the laws of human nature,
我们也要尊重人心中的规律
respect the objective laws of the industry,
尊重行业的客观规律
and many things cannot be achieved by brute force alone,
而且很多事情靠蛮干是没有办法突破的
within this system.
你在这个系统内
If you don’t break out of your conventional thinking,
你如果思维不跳出来
you’ll never be able to achieve multiple goals at once.
你是永远不可能同时做到几个要素的
As for the breakthrough strategy mentioned earlier,
因为刚才说的破局思路
it’s either through leverage,
要么以利
or through ingenuity.
要么以巧
Neither of these is likely to be accomplished in the short term.
他可能都不是短期能够做到的
From a short-term perspective,
那么短期视角来看
if you want to achieve something,
如果你想要得到某种东西
you have to be willing to let go.
你就要敢于放弃
You'll have to pay a certain price
你就要支付某些代价
Otherwise, you might end up wanting everything
不然的话你可能既要又要还要
And ultimately get nothing
最终什么都没有得到
That's the first point
这是第一点
It's akin to a philosophy of life
他类似于一个生活哲学
The second point is that we shouldn't view things in isolation
那么第二点呢是我们不要用孤立的眼光
We shouldn't look at things in a fragmented way
我们不要用分散的眼光去看待事物
We should try to view things through the lens of system theory
我们要尽可能的用系统论的眼光
When examining a particular issue
去看待某一个事情
When you can actually do it, you have truly achieved it. You have mastered the field comprehensively. Because in complex systems, many components, the elements are interconnected, either positively or negatively.
那当你能够做到的时候 其实你就做到了 在这个领域中实现了融会贯通 因为复杂系统中很多东西 它的要素之间都是互相勾点的 或者正相关或者负相关
Each element is widely connected to others.
每一个要素和其他要素是广泛联系的
Pulling one thread moves the entire body.
那牵一发而动全身
So if you can adopt a holistic perspective on resource allocation,
所以你如果能够用一个资源分配的全局视角啊
Not limited to just one or two costs
不再局限于某一个代价或者某两个代价
But rather approach the complex system with a holistic perspective
而是用一个全局的思路去看待这个复杂系统
Only then can you possibly achieve the optimal solution
你才有可能得到最优解
So
所以呢
We should strive to view things through the lens of system theory
我们要尽可能的用系统论的方式去看待事物
This is also a way of thinking that many high-cognition individuals can achieve
这也是很多高认知的人士能够做到的一种思维
A thinking habit
思维习惯
What is the third insight?
第三点的启示是什么呢
Guiding consciousness
指导意识
When you look at things from a long-term perspective
当你用一个长期视角来看的话
thinking about potentially dedicating ten years to it
也就是我可能能投入在这件事情上10年
or even spending your entire career on this company
或者我可能要做这公司做一辈子
then you shouldn’t let your thinking be confined
那么你就不要被思维所局限住
if you want to break through
你如果想要去突破
the impossible triangle
不可能三角的话
you need to broaden your horizons to find a way out
你就要开拓视野去找这个破局方式
to find a way out
找破局方式
which brings us back to what we talked about earlier
又回到了刚才说的
Either break through with force
要么以力破
Look for resources outside the system
看系统外有没有资源
See if there are ways to get external support
系统外有没有为你输血的方式
What is actually more encouraged is To explore the possibility of advancing through technological evolution Through the iteration of methodologies By enhancing your management skills Or improving your management capabilities And also by boosting the system through institutional innovation
其实更鼓励大家去做的是 你要看有没有可能通过技术演进 通过方法论的迭代 通过提升你的管理技巧 或者提升你的管理能力 以及包括通过制度创新来提升这个系统内
The efficiency of transformation between different elements
不同要素之间的转化效率
And on a longer timescale
然后呢在一个更长的时间尺度上
While optimizing the interactions between the various components of the system
同时实现这个系统各个要素之间的优化好
The final point
那么最后一点呢
Actually, it reminds me of our ancient paintings
其实我想到了咱们这边的古画啊
Or some ancient wisdom in daily life
或者一些古老的生活智慧
Using an ancient perspective to view the world
用古老的看待世界的方式
Promoting the principle of moderation, right?
去推崇中庸之道的对吧
If you look at it from the perspective of the impossible triangle
如果你用不可能三角来看的话
It does make some sense.
它是有一些道理的
Why is that?
为什么呢
Because, first of all, when this system exists,
因为首先当这个系统存在
It's impossible,
不可能
when a triangle has several mutually negative factors,
三角存在不同几个互相负相关的要素的时候
if you forcefully increase one of the metrics,
你强行拉高其中的一个指标
if you insist on pursuing an extreme value in one area,
强行追求其中某一个极值
it could end up being counterproductive.
很可能会得不偿失
Because when we look at a triangle and see it can achieve such a state,
因为当我们看一个三角能够达到这样的时候
It might have the largest area
它可能面积才是最大的
If the sides are of fixed length
如果边边长是固定的话
If you forcibly increase one side
你如果强行的拉高一个边长
It will turn into a narrow triangle with less area
它会变成一个窄三角的面积
There could be a loss
有可能会损失
For example, the more money and less work we talked about earlier Being close to home If we look at it from this perspective When can I achieve the maximum area That is, your job satisfaction or the overall benefits of your job which means finding a job where the pay isn't too low
就比如说刚才说的钱多事儿少 离家近 如果从这个角度去讲的话 我什么时候能达能达到一个面积的最最大值 也就是你的工作幸福度 或者你的工作的综合收益 那就是找一个钱也不太少
and it's not too far from home
离家不远不近
with a moderate amount of overtime
同时加班不多不少
or working hours
或者劳动时长
where the level of effort is manageable
这个辛苦程度还可以的工作
This is the first point
那么这是第一点
which sometimes refers to the total area
就是我们有时候用总面积的啊
From the perspective of overall happiness or total benefits,
总幸福度或者总收益的角度去看的话
the middle way makes sense.
中庸之道是有道理的
Another point is when you're not using the approach of outsmarting the situation,
那么另外一点呢是当你不是用以巧破局的思路
but rather the approach of improving efficiency.
而是提升效率的思路
If you constantly borrow from outside the system, like from wealthy merchants,
而是你总是向系统外去借富商的话
you might actually, on a larger scale,
那么实际上你有可能在更大的尺度上
be increasing the fragility of the entire matter,
是在增加整件事的脆弱性
or raising the overall risk in your environment.
或者拉高你所在环境的整体的风险度
For example, let's go back to that point I mentioned earlier.
比如说还是回到刚才那一点
Right?
对吧啊
The 996 work schedule
996这件事
When a project's scope
当一个项目它的范围
time and cost form an impossible triangle
时间成本达到了一个不可能三角
if you want to break through it
你想突破它的时候
you can sacrifice your employees' health, right?
你可以牺牲你员工的健康对吧
sacrificing employees' health
那么牺牲员工健康
on the surface it might not seem like a cost you bear
表面上看好像不是你支付的代价
but it also damages the project itself There's a possible error rate. Due to a decline in everyone's energy. If everyone's focus drops, Long-term 996 work hours might cause your project
但是他同时损害的是你这个项目 有可能的错误率 因为大家的精力下降 大家的这个专注度下降的话 长期996是有可能让你这个项目
To have continuous errors.
不断的出错的
Additionally, innovation capabilities might decline.
另外呢创新能力有可能下降
Moreover, your HR employer brand might suffer.
还有就是你这个hr的雇主品牌有可能会下降
Meaning, people will know you as a notorious
也就是大家都知道你是一个臭名昭著的
Company that doesn't care about employee health.
不把员工的健康当回事的公司
So, as we mentioned earlier, social development, right?
那么还有就是刚才说到社会发展对吧
Efficiency, fairness, and equality,
效率公平平等
Or something like growth rates,
或者我们说嗯类似于增长率
If you can't achieve them all at the same time,
你没有办法同时兼顾的话
You might sacrifice environmental protection,
你可以牺牲环境保护
You might do this by damaging the environment,
你通过破坏环境的方式去做这件事
But in a larger system perspective,
但实际上在更大的系统来看
That is, not confining this system to society alone,
也就是不把这个系统局限在社会
But also including nature within it,
而是把大自然也囊括进来的话
Actually, you are overextending your country's development potential.
其实你是在透支你整个国家的发展潜力
You are overextending the health of the overall environment.
你是在透支大环境的健康程度
And you might invite some uncontrollable systemic risks.
以及你可能会引来一些不可控的系统性的风险
So I think the principle of moderation has its merits.
所以我觉得呃中庸之道它是有一定道理的
However, moderation is not an absolute truth.
但是呢中庸之道不是一个绝对真理
Why is that?
为什么呢
There are also two opposing arguments. The first argument is about life and society. Sometimes, you have to make some seemingly unreasonable choices. Why is that? Because you're not the only person in this world. Sometimes you need to work hard for others.
同样也有两个相抗的理由 第一个理由是人生和社会 有的时候就是要做出一些不不合理的选择 为什么呢 因为这个世界上不是只有你一个人 你有的时候要为别人去努力
Or sometimes time doesn’t wait for anyone.
或者呢你有的时候时间不等人
You have to strive for a specific window of time.
你要为一个时间窗口而努力
Once that window passes,
这个时间窗口一旦错过
the opportunity is gone.
那么机会就不再有了
The likelihood of achieving your goal will significantly decrease.
你想做成某件事的概率就会大大的降低
For instance, when it comes to choosing a job.
比如说呢刚才说到这个选择选择工作这件事
If we consider a job's salary,
如果我们把一个工作的工资
promotion opportunities, and working hours as an impossible
晋升机会以及劳动时长这三者看作一个不可能
triangle,
三角啊
it often plays out this way.
很多时候都是这样的
As I mentioned earlier,
那么我刚才说了
if you approach it with a more moderate and reasonable method,
如果用比较中庸之道的比较合理的方式
by considering the marginal cost,
考虑边际成本的方式去做的话
you should look for promotion opportunities,
你应该找的就是晋升空间
where the salary is also decent.
有一些工资呢还可以
Then, jobs with not too long overtime hours
然后呢加班时间不太长的工作
But often that's not the case
但是很多时候不是这样的
For instance, when you have a mortgage
比如说当你有了房贷的时候
Or when your small family is striving for something
你们小家庭在为为了某个事情去努力的时候
At such times, the pressure on your cash flow is significant
这个时候你的现金流压力很大
So you might need to prioritize securing your salary
那么你有可能就得极致的保你的工资
For which you might end up taking a job with limited promotion prospects But pays you a decent amount now And involves a high number of working hours At this point, you don't need to worry about marginal costs. Instead, what you need to do is focus on the present moment. You should meet the needs of this stage of your life.
你为此可能会付出找一个晋升空间不是很大 但是现在能给你不少钱 以及找一个劳动时长也很高的工作 那么这个时候就不需要考虑边际成本了 而是现在你需要此时此刻 就满足你的这个这个阶段的人生需求
Another point is, for example,
那另外一点呢是比如说啊
When you graduate at 22,
当你22岁刚毕业的时候
you don't have the pressure of a family, right?
这个时候你没有家庭压力对吧
And you are young,
然后呢你很年轻
your energy is still abundant.
你的精力还很充沛
To put it bluntly,
也就是我们说的残酷一点
You might have to pay a certain health cost
你可以付出一定的健康代价
In that case, your optimal solution might be
那这个时候有可能你的最优解是
I'm aiming for promotion opportunities or a faster promotion track
我就是为了晋升机会或者晋升速度
And I'm willing to sacrifice my salary
然后牺牲掉我的工资
And my labor market
以及啊我的劳动市场
I can take a job with a very promising future
我可以为了一个前景非常好的工作
Listening to the grand plans my boss paints
听老板给我画的大饼
And then accept the current situation where
然后呢接受此时此刻刚一进去
The salary is not very high
工资不是很高
And I have to work overtime every day
而且每天还要加班
Life and society are sometimes like this
人生和社会有的时候就是这样的
We need to ignore marginal benefits
需要我们去忽视边际效益
And focus on elevating one particular curve at a certain stage
然后呢在某个阶段去拉高其中的某一个曲线
To achieve what I want at this stage
然后来达到现阶段我想要的东西
Because opportunities are fleeting
因为机会是稍纵即逝的
Another point is Why the middle way is not always right The middle way suggests that In ancient times, the pie couldn't be made very big In an agrarian society Technology was not the primary productive force
另外一点呢 为什么中庸之道有的时候不一定是对的 是因为中庸之道提出来的是 古代古代的盘子是做不大的 农业社会 大家科技科学技术不是第一生产力
Human labor was the primary productive force
人力才是第一生产力
And there was no globalization
同时呢也没有全球化
At that time, it was hard to find wealthy merchants outside the system
那那个时候呢系统外的富商找不到
And you couldn't quickly improve
同时呢你也没有办法很快速的提高
The conversion efficiency between different elements
不同要素之间的转化效率
Scientific development back then might have relied on luck
科技发展那个时候有可能靠蒙
Rather than a country's regular R&D investment
而不是靠常常规的一个国家有研发投入
Steadily producing scientific research results
稳定地输出一些这个科研成果
But things are different now
但是现在不一样了
We live in a modern society
现在我们是现代社会
In modern society
那么在现代社会
Whether you are a country
不管你是一个国家
A company
你是一个呃公司
Or an individual
你还是个个人
We can use routine and institutionalized methodologies
我们都可以日常化的制度化的方法论
To steadily enhance our capabilities
化的去稳步的提升自己的能力
To conduct R&D
去啊搞研发
To iterate on methodologies
去迭代方法论
To continuously fill information gaps
去不断地补足信息上的不足
And to constantly improve your own abilities
以及呢去不断的提升你自己的能力
Now we have various methods
现在我们有各种各样的方法
Various tools to achieve this
各种各样的工具去做到这一点
So you don't need to think
所以你就不需要去想
I need to hold back
我做事情要收着点
It's good enough
差不多得了啊
I don't need to pursue the maximum benefit Actually, people with this mindset often lose out You need to see that Modern society provides you with all sorts of tools Gives you ample ways
我不要追求这个最大的收益 其实现在我们这样思路的人往往会吃亏 那么你要看到 实际上现代社会给了你这样那样的工具 给了你非常充足的方式
To break through the impossible triangle in different fields
去突破不同领域中的不可能三角
So
所以呢
I think a modern person should not limit themselves to a certain predicament
我觉得现如今一个没有更好的现代人的心态啊
But should always look beyond the system
不应该把自己局限在某一个困境里面
Is there any room for improvement
而是应该始终再向系统外去看
Is there any potential for enhancement
我还有没有改进的可能性
Rather than thinking like the ancients
我还有没有提升的可能性
It's good enough
而不是说像古人想的一样啊
People shouldn't have too many desires
说差不多得了啊
People shouldn't go against nature
人应该这个不要有那么多的欲望
They should respect the way of nature
然后呢人不应该逆天而行
That time is long gone
应该尊重自然之道啊
We have the potential to make better choices
现在已经不是那个时代了
Alright, I'm Lao Jiang
我们有可能做出更好的选择
I'm an UPloader who likes to ponder things
嗯好那么我是老蒋
And share my thoughts and ideas
我是一个喜欢琢磨事儿
This is actually a rather spontaneous topic
喜欢输出自己观点和想法的这样一名up主
It's been on my mind for some time
那么这个呢其实是比较偶然的一期选题呃
Thinking about what the impossible triangle really is
我在脑子已经转了一段时间啊
So I decided to share some of my thoughts
在想不可能三角它到底是什么
Some ideas
那于是呢就想把自己的一些思考成果
And share them with you all
一些想法
If you find this video inspiring
然后分享给大家
And you like it Please give me a Triple Combo And follow me You can also leave your thoughts On this video in the comments section Including any discussions Alright See you in the next video Take care
那么如果你觉得这期视频给了你启发 而且你喜欢你可以啊 给我一个三连 然后关注我 你也可以在评论区留下 你对这期视频的一些想法 包括一些探讨 好了啊 我们下期再见